[SPEAKER_00]: My concern is, eh, uh, to do jhāna is, of course, my daily practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You told it many times, how I should, uh, during the day, I should, uh, just... Apart from that, uh, my, uh, routine meditation in the morning, just being aware of the, uh, breath, and then the periphery body, where the breath depends on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is the summary of... this should be the summary of my meditation, now that I'm in my practice, now that I am...
[SPEAKER_00]: Going in two days.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I would like to have a kind of summary for that, or the guidance, maybe.
[SPEAKER_04]: In a sense of what to do when you're back.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, how to...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I saw here for two or three weeks, but like a summary for the... What do you think?
[SPEAKER_02]: You can be aware of your body, you can be aware of your breath, your body, but why are you doing that?
[SPEAKER_00]: My ultimate goal is to get the right feel, of course, and
[SPEAKER_00]: Just try not to do things out of desire and aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would be the...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, how are those things done?
[SPEAKER_04]: Can you accidentally, unintentionally, do things out of greed, aversion and delusion?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, they come up and then I shouldn't react to that greed which is coming up, which is just... Not sure that react would be the best description.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not about reaction.
[SPEAKER_04]: See, reaction is, oh, I just reacted.
[SPEAKER_04]: Somebody scares you, you react.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can't prevent that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Act.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, act.
[SPEAKER_04]: Act and react is different.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's my point.
[SPEAKER_04]: Can those things happen by accident?
[SPEAKER_04]: They can't.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, greed, aversion, delusion cannot accidentally occur when I forgot or something.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: They're always on the level of your choice.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, they're always chosen.
[SPEAKER_00]: That means, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: I choose to act out of greed?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: You do.
[SPEAKER_04]: On some level, you do.
[SPEAKER_04]: You have to be doing.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's the point.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like people...
[SPEAKER_04]: The only way to start recognizing such choices is to start looking
[SPEAKER_04]: Choices per se, in general.
[SPEAKER_04]: But people think like, oh, I haven't...
[SPEAKER_04]: I acted out of greed, aversion, delusion, because I wasn't focused enough, or concentrated, or calm enough.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, you acted because you chose to act.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the only way to get closer to that recognition, when you choose to act out of these things, is to keep pondering on the motivation behind your actions, intentions, and choices you make throughout the day.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, as I said, being calm is nice, it's fine, and you can calm down, sure, but that has nothing to do with your choices.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if you think that greed, aversion, delusion comes out of, you know, accidental non-calmness or a slip of the mind or something, they don't.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: They came because you chose to allow them to enter.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So that's what you need to look for the problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, on top of that, if calming helps you reflect further on your choices, yes, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you have to abandon the view that calming will make me choose better.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, it won't.
[SPEAKER_04]: Value of certain choices and value against certain other choices, pondering on those values and importance and danger and peril, that will help you choose better.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that peril will not be seen by itself and it will not come as a result of, you know, watching the nostril.
[SPEAKER_04]: It will come if you make the effort to see it and think about it and remind yourself of everything that the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this reminding is also, of course, an issue for me.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, it is... That's really where the practice is.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like bhāvana, as in keep it in the being, maintain it, a certain context that you need to be knowing, be aware of it and clarifying it further.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, Bhāvanā is not on the level of calming, calming, until the experience of the pleasant kind comes over, and then, I don't even think about greed, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, that was never the problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: The problem is, could you think about greed, aversion, delusion?
[SPEAKER_04]: And the answer is yes, because the danger has not been cultivated enough, seen enough, understood enough.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you can do all the calming you want, the moment that calming goes away, you don't know where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: The problem was, you are still unwittingly, yet intentionally, choosing greed, aversion, delusion on the level of body, speech or mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what it's saying to me as well, is if you are watching your intentions, your choices that you're making, and valuing the right choices and devaluing the wrong ones, then you are automatically, or by default, what starts to happen is you are aware of your body, what you are physically doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_02]: So you are aware of your physical actions.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're aware of what you're saying.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're aware of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: That comes out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't have to be aware of the body, hoping that you're going to know why you are doing things, because you're watching your knees, you're watching your abdomen rise and fall, and that's going to reveal why you are doing something.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to ask yourself, why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, and that's really what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you want a method for mindfulness, it's that question.
[SPEAKER_04]: That results in mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not the sensation watching or belly-bobbing or whatever else people do.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, that, that, that...
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like, you do that expecting experience.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why am I doing what I'm doing?
[SPEAKER_04]: See, that question already puts you in a state of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, if you keep pushing further with such questioning, you will arrive at certain universal truths, such as, oh, whatever I'm doing is in order to avoid pain, prolong pleasure, choices I make, no matter how subtle or coarse, they always have to be rooted in in those three principles.
[SPEAKER_04]: Greed, aversion, delusion, or non-greed, non-aversion, non-delusion.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's where the problem is, and that's where the solution is.
[SPEAKER_00]: The issue is that during the day, for example, suddenly I get, I become aware that I'm thinking about
[SPEAKER_00]: Unpleasant thought, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm angry about something.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the place where I should then practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, like, the whole point is to recognize that the practice is on the level of that liability to angry thoughts or lustful thoughts, not the actual one.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sure, actual one, but that's already too late.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, so if it's...
[SPEAKER_04]: Actual anger or lust, yeah, you got to restrain it, not act out of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: But then, when it's not there, you shouldn't start thinking, ah, okay, I dealt with the problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: As the Buddha would often say, a monk would review his mind and ask himself, can non-arisen unwholesome things arise in this mind?
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, oh, yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: And now, you start cultivating the danger if such things arise.
[SPEAKER_04]: How would they arise?
[SPEAKER_04]: Through what choices you make?
[SPEAKER_04]: Little thing here, little thing there.
[SPEAKER_04]: Before you know it, mind is filled with lust and you're accepting it.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it's always on that level of welcoming, delighting, entertaining, engaging with mentally.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that is a matter of choice.
[SPEAKER_04]: Now, of course, if somebody is not restrained in the body,
[SPEAKER_04]: These subtle choices on the level of their thoughts will not be seen.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, nevertheless, they are choices.
[SPEAKER_04]: They are things you choose to allow, so to speak, in a sense of... have a welcoming attitude towards.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why you have to really, like, hammer in that sense of danger, so that you uproot the attitude of this is nice, this is good, this is friendly, this is for me.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, you you would arrive at that, yeah, if you spend, obviously, if you keep the precepts, guide the sense doors, and then, throughout the day, whatever you're doing, ask yourself questions, endure doubt, if it's unclear,
[SPEAKER_04]: But fundamentally recognize that whatever you choose to do on the level of body, speech, or mind, cannot happen accidentally.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's always on the level of your choice.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thus, at the same time, see, it feels like, oh, this is so overwhelming, but at the same time, it's actually easier.
[SPEAKER_04]: It becomes easier, because you realize, okay, so I don't need to worry about these things accidentally happening, affecting me, oppressing me, and now I have to deal with them on and on, because they just accidentally came in.
[SPEAKER_04]: That becomes impossible.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the clearer you become in sort of this type of bhāvana, this type of cultivation, the more confident you are, because you know, oh, no, no, it doesn't matter what circumstances are coming this way, good or bad, I'm the one who opens the door.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the clearer you are with that, the clearer the door becomes, and the more confident and safe you feel, because you won't open the door once you know the danger.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if you keep perpetuating the view that these disturbances of the mind happen accidentally because you were not concentrated enough or calm enough, you keep perpetuating the view that the problem comes on its... from outside on its own and you have nothing to do with it, you just have to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, eh... and that's not the case.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then you will always feel undermined by it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Doesn't matter how... how well your concentration is developed and commitment to practice, you're always going to feel undermined because you... you undermine yourself.
[SPEAKER_04]: By putting it externally,
[SPEAKER_04]: Whatever happens, if it's... if it's sort of unpleasant, you won't know where the problem was and you would think it was because of the circumstances and then you would try to double down in your calmness and concentration and ignoring and covering up, so that these things don't arise.
[SPEAKER_04]: But they were never the problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: The problem was your intentional choice.
[SPEAKER_04]: Ignorant one, lustful one or angry one.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if there is an anger in your mind, thoughts came up, yeah, you didn't ask for it, but you have a choice now.
[SPEAKER_04]: Am I trying to get rid of this, acting out of anger?
[SPEAKER_04]: Am I acting out of anger further towards what I, you know...
[SPEAKER_04]: Am I projected as the reason of my anger, or am I able to just endure it, you know, let the mind kick and scream, but not engage with such thoughts?
[SPEAKER_04]: Not try to, you know, get rid of them, because you can't, but you can certainly not welcome them.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, no, you can be there in front of the door, shout and scream, but you are not welcome inside.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, your attitude of non-welcoming, that's the line, that's what you need to develop, but not further, and not less than that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the only way you can develop that, and develop clarity in regards to that attitude, is keep looking for it, keep asking questions, keep reviewing.
[SPEAKER_04]: It won't happen magically on account of a concentration experience or something.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: That instruction, that the two factors for the arising of right view, being the instruction from another, the word of another, and yoniso manisikāra, which is like being able to know your intentions behind your actions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, know the origin, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Knowing the origin of your actions.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, having the instruction and then watching what are you doing.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, yeah, see where it's rooted.
[SPEAKER_04]: But what's the... what's usually the problem with that, with yoniso manasikāra?
[SPEAKER_02]: The view, the common view.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so say, like you describe this to somebody, yoniso manasikāra is knowing the origin of your intentions, of your choices.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why people can't see that?
[SPEAKER_04]: Why would that require so much explanation as it does, and people would still do it wrongly?
[SPEAKER_04]: What's the... where's the issue?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, because you're so absorbed in your sense world, senses, unrestrained, never have any self-reflection, never pause, just going with whatever feels good, avoiding whatever feels bad.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how can you see your mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you step back to see your intentions?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, but, like, even the person, if they're not restrained, and you tell them about yonisumanasikāra, the origin of your intentions, they can get their head around.
[SPEAKER_04]: But why that, whatever they get their head around, why that will not be yonisumanasikāra?
[SPEAKER_04]: Why that will not be the origin?
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be abstract.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why?
[SPEAKER_04]: Why would it be abstract?
[SPEAKER_04]: So, let's just stick with the origin of your action.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it needs to be attended properly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Let's say it like that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And when people think, if people have not been sense restrained, guarded of the sense doors, when they think they're attending it properly, they're not.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why?
[SPEAKER_04]: They're turning it into an object.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's exactly the point.
[SPEAKER_04]: They basically attend to it as another object of their senses, even thoughts.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's not what it is.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, they cannot see anything more refined than object of what I'm attending, because that's where the mind is.
[SPEAKER_04]: Mind takes that as a threshold of what is.
[SPEAKER_04]: And mind takes that as a threshold of what is, because the lack of the sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_04]: And when I say lack of virtue and sense restraint, I mean properly, done properly.
[SPEAKER_04]: In other words, endured properly, sufficiently.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it's easy for people to be virtuous when they adopt the external set of circumstances, tradition, community, and so on.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, you just stick to the external behavior, but you haven't taken on the virtue.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why the factor of sīlabata paramāsa is one of the first three to go, if you start doing things rightly.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if you have taken it on, in a sense of you are enduring doubt, you are still questioning the intentions behind your action, you don't just not do or do because the rules or the tradition says so.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if things are endured on the right level, then yes, your mind will cease to maintain the notion that the only thing that is real, the only thing that exists, is the one that I can attend to or access through my senses.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, yoniso, meaning womb, manasikāra means the origin of your attention.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, whatever you choose to attend, i.e.
[SPEAKER_04]: direct your attention towards, yoniso of it is at the back of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's where this attention is coming from.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you cannot attend that, in the same sense as you said before, an eye cannot see itself.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just impossible.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yet, the knowledge that the eye is there as a prerequisite for seeing, can be developed.
[SPEAKER_04]: As a present absence.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: It is simultaneously present, but it can never be directly present as an object of your attention.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yet, it is present as a basis for your attention.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's that subtlety.
[SPEAKER_04]: That, again, you can reason, and you can abstract it, and you can get your head around it, but unless the mind has been developed through correct endurance first, it will be just another thing you attend to.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it won't be the yoniso of your manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to kind of describe that in a practical way, in a way which isn't abstract, one could say it's like an absence of
[SPEAKER_01]: Greed, aversion and distraction, this present absence, in the sense that by not conceiving this mind, not turning it into an object in front of me, one is seeing that it's arisen by itself.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, but, like I say, not turning it into an object,
[SPEAKER_04]: It can become your object.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: That thought becomes your object now.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you cannot just make a choice to attend to it.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can recognize what is a necessary basis for developing recognition of such attention.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the necessary basis would be taking on the virtue rightly, sensory strain rightly, enduring it on the right level.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the best example would be, like, you know, the unpleasant state of doubt.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just generally, how do you go about it when you're doubtful?
[SPEAKER_04]: Whether doubtful about rules or precepts or... How do you go about it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Do you take it for granted that you must get rid of it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or are you able to endure it without acting out of it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Enduring it without acting out of it is closer to yoniso manasikāra than you pondering about yoniso manasikāra having acted out of doubt.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, as a whole, putting, not just yourself, putting your entire existence in question, because it is always in question.
[SPEAKER_04]: The impermanence is one giant question mark that undermines you.
[SPEAKER_04]: And doubt exemplifies that.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why doubt is so unpleasant and people always try to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even if it's externally not that significant, the experience of doubt is always, like, cannot be tolerated, cannot be endured, because, as I said, it exemplifies that underlying condition.
[SPEAKER_04]: of being undermined by things that are not in your control, that are uncertain.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if you're able to endure things on that level, not act out, i.e.
[SPEAKER_04]: not break precepts, but not give in to overly defining either, in order to get rid of the doubt, yeah, see, you are seeing the origins now of what you're attending and why you're attending.
[SPEAKER_04]: But the only way reason you're seeing and you're getting to know them is because you're enduring them.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can't just choose to attend them.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, yoniso manasikāra is the result of correctly developing your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you could choose to develop... to attend to everything you said with craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: It becomes an object of attention, thus it becomes affected with craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's an interesting way to put doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Doubt exemplifies your existence.
[SPEAKER_02]: The big question mark shows you the nature of this, what's happening, your situation, and then you're trying to solve it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're running about trying to solve that.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's anxiety there, complexity.
[SPEAKER_02]: What should I do?
[SPEAKER_02]: How should I do it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Where should I go?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, doubts... so doubts... why is doubt a hindrance?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, it's a good question.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's one of the hindrances, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Anybody has a thought on that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is doubt a hindrance?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it entails
[SPEAKER_01]: Being moved without...
[SPEAKER_01]: It entails losing perspective on the nature of one's experience by...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, for example, you said the idea of trying to solve this uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, one can only... Why?
[SPEAKER_04]: Why would one try to solve the uncertainty?
[SPEAKER_04]: Where would those acts be rooted in?
[SPEAKER_00]: Aversion.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_04]: Aversion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, one could...
[SPEAKER_04]: Pain, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Aversion to pain.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, doubt is a hindrance, because you want to get rid of the pain of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, doubt hinders you, because you take for granted your aversion to discomfort.
[SPEAKER_03]: You act out of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: In the same sense, centrality is a hindrance, because you take for granted your delight in comfort, pleasure.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why you're hindered.
[SPEAKER_04]: It doesn't hinder you by itself.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're responsible for being hindered.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, doubt is not necessarily... it doesn't have to be a hindrance.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just putting things in question.
[SPEAKER_04]: But the thing is, see, putting things in question does not necessarily need to cause you existential pain.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if it does cause you existential pain, to that extent it's a hindrance, because to that extent you're still resisting the pain.
[SPEAKER_04]: But what would be a difference between doubt as a fetter and as a hindrance?
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the fetter of doubt, kind of on the level of what we just said, that taking on the virtue and so on, on account of external authority, doubt, as a fetter, is on the same level.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which, of course, it is, because it pertains to the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there's choice involved in the hindrance.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fetter is something which is a result of
[SPEAKER_01]: This is just a lack of prior discernment, whereas the hindrance is something which you are actively engaging with.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: Vetter is something obviously actively maintained.
[SPEAKER_03]: That fetter of doubt is bound up with the other two first fetters, the personality view and, you know, wrongly holding the virtues and the duties and the habits and the practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the whole business of personality view, rooted in this assumption, I am, I exist, this is myself, that can never be fully and totally clarified and made certain, because
[SPEAKER_03]: You exist within a situation, always.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so, you cannot step outside of that, outside of your experience, in order to gain... A definition for yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the whole business of existence is, by definition, ambiguous.
[SPEAKER_03]: And therefore uncertain.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is why the second factor of the personality view is precisely doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, it seems to me that, in order to deal with this doubt, when it's done wrongly, one is going to grasp after external patterns already set up, whether it is daily routines, virtue, precepts, and all the rest of it,
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, one just keeps going around in circles and circles.
[SPEAKER_03]: When personality view is seen as it is, then there is this timelessness of dhamma with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the whole point of, I have to do this in order to get that, either some insight or some calm or freedom from doubt, this sort of time interference which sits there, keeps reinforcing the doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you do something now, hoping for a result in the future, but you will never be quite clear whether what you're doing is right.
[SPEAKER_03]: It needs to be seen.
[SPEAKER_03]: Basically,
[SPEAKER_03]: In a more direct sense.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just...
[SPEAKER_04]: So that's the...
[SPEAKER_04]: But why, why... That's all fine.
[SPEAKER_04]: But why would that doubt... Why is it a fetter still?
[SPEAKER_04]: See, somebody who is free from a fetter of doubt, their existence is still in the same question.
[SPEAKER_04]: It hasn't been resolved.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sotāpanna still has plenty of work to do.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: But he's free from the fettering aspect of that doubt.
[SPEAKER_04]: What is the fettering aspect of the doubt as a fetter?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, when personality view or assumption of self is seen as impermanent,
[SPEAKER_03]: Which is the case for the sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, with that, that fetter of doubt, wanting to make your existence certain and having a stability there, this is what I am, this is myself, and I want to fix that forever, that whole attempt is finished.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because the impermanence of that underlying assumption of self is seen.
[SPEAKER_03]: So doubt doesn't fetter him anymore, because the whole notion of him or her is sort of
[SPEAKER_03]: Comes and goes now.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, what happens then, when doubt is present for him, for such person?
[SPEAKER_04]: What's the difference between...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, doubt is present for somebody who is not free from the fettering aspect of doubt?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, doubt is present for somebody who is free from the fettering aspect of doubt.
[SPEAKER_04]: What's the practical difference between two of them?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, for somebody who is not free from the fetter of doubt, in the sense that hindrance might be fueling all those lower fetters still, but when the fetters are out of the way, those hindrances are actually being more properly seen for the first time as hindrances.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, but that's again taking one... but between the two, what's the difference, just in terms of doubt?
[SPEAKER_04]: Between the one who is fettered by the doubt and the one who isn't.
[SPEAKER_04]: Both experiencing doubt, one is fettered by the experience of doubt, the other one isn't.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Where is the precise difference between the two examples?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, the precise difference is that the fetter of doubt is the result of not seeing dhamma.
[SPEAKER_03]: But someone who sees dhamma doesn't have that doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, he might still be due to sensuality and the other hidden...
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just that, again, that the answer is on the level of why he is not fettered.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, he's not fettered because he sees the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_04]: Fine.
[SPEAKER_04]: We covered that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: But what's the difference between the one who has seen the dhamma and it's not fettered by the doubt that is present, and another one who is fettered by the doubt that's present, who hasn't seen the dhamma?
[SPEAKER_04]: Not why, but what is the difference between the two?
[SPEAKER_04]: Practically exemplified, which is exactly back onto the question, why that doubt?
[SPEAKER_04]: How, or rather, what is the fetter of the fetter of the doubt?
[SPEAKER_04]: What is the fettering aspect?
[SPEAKER_04]: That would be the difference between the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: The way they go about it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Gone?
[SPEAKER_04]: Stay more?
[SPEAKER_03]: One tries to deal with it, and the other recognizes it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And where is... where would that be rooted?
[SPEAKER_04]: In aversion to pain.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_04]: Aversion to pain.
[SPEAKER_04]: Aversion to pain, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Overall, it would be rooted basically in a view.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, he still puts... the one that is fettered by the presence of doubt, takes for granted, and that's the assumption, that's the view, that's why it's a fetter, takes for granted that getting rid of doubt
[SPEAKER_04]: It must be done.
[SPEAKER_04]: It should be welcomed.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's his duty to do so, to clarify it.
[SPEAKER_04]: In other words, he has all these views, or a view, a wrong view, that justifies dealing with the doubt.
[SPEAKER_04]: While in reality, all he justifies is aversion towards pain, acting towards getting rid of the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's why that is rooted in taking yourself for granted, ay, dhyātavāda, and it is rooted in the external sets of norms and circumstances and duties that you've taken on.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's on the same level.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, by assuming that you should, you have right, and it must be done, the doubt must be get rid of, you then adopt external set of behavior, almost magically, a magical connection.
[SPEAKER_04]: If I don't do this, oh, because I did this, this is what happened.
[SPEAKER_04]: All rooted in simply not acknowledging that the pain needs to be endured first.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that brings me to another little point I want to mention.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the first three fetters, they're together.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you could maybe theoretically kind of differentiate what comes first, but overall, they arise together, they exist together, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it wouldn't be one leads to the other that leads to the third one.
[SPEAKER_04]: They're just there, because they're kind of three aspects of the same externally projected attitude.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that is the in common to all three.
[SPEAKER_04]: The external assumption of yourself, as in yourself exist independent of this experience as a whole,
[SPEAKER_04]: The external dependence on the sets of norms, behaviors, authorities, not because you chose to do so and then feeling the weight and the uncertainty of your choice.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, of course, the external engagement in order to prevent the pain of doubt.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if you start uprooting this external assumption on any of these three hindrances, the other two will be uprooted as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, fetters, sorry.
[SPEAKER_04]: The other two will be uprooted as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that would be the difference between somebody who is experiencing doubt, without being fettered by it, and somebody who is fettered by it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the one who is not fettered by it, means he has endured it long enough, so that his mind has calmed down within that kicking and screaming of trying to get rid of the existential doubt, that's the most unpleasant thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: And once it calms down within kicking and screaming, by not acting out of it, you then get to see it as an enduring phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, as unpleasant as it is, you see that it has arisen and thus it has to cease.
[SPEAKER_04]: And your clarification of it, engagement, seeking the answer just to get rid of the pain of it, would just be to cover up.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you know that.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you won't be fettered by it.
[SPEAKER_04]: You'll still be pressured by it, hence the hindrance of doubt.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you still need to train your mind on more subtler levels to not act out, to not welcome and so on, but you're not fettered because you cannot adopt that view again.
[SPEAKER_04]: Putting your getting rid of the pain first, as a valuable, as a valid thing, and thinking doubt just came externally, and if I address it... No, you realize... No.
[SPEAKER_04]: Any direction of my effort towards external circumstances, in order to deal with the doubt, cannot be conceived anymore, because you don't... you understood that... you see the doubt doesn't come from external world.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, why would you be addressing it there?
[SPEAKER_04]: And people who have been addressing it there, is the one who haven't seen where it came from, because they haven't endured it long enough.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, and that kind of comes back to, you know, I must, I'm sure we said it before, the whole, like, sotāpati and the three fetters.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, you need to know, you know, what the Buddha taught, what, you know, clarify what the what the fetters are, what the ātavāda is, impermanence and so on.
[SPEAKER_04]: But fundamentally, people don't get the right view.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not because they don't have the enough information and utterance of another.
[SPEAKER_04]: In terms of what the right view is, they don't get it, because they haven't endured things sufficiently long enough on that level.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's usually taken for granted.
[SPEAKER_04]: It must be avoided, must be prevented, must be managed, must be covered up, must be dealt with.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's why, as we said before, that's why yoniso manasikāra is not developed.
[SPEAKER_04]: Things are not endured rightly, on the right level.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, here's a question.
[SPEAKER_03]: Suppose somebody wants to deliberately move towards that fetter of doubt by keeping the question, who am I, alive and making that as the main practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is that a valid approach?
[SPEAKER_04]: It could be, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: It depends on what other things that person does.
[SPEAKER_04]: Do they do that cultivation of that attitude paired with with sense restraint, guarding of the sense doors,
[SPEAKER_04]: Not acting out towards other hindrances as well, and then keep themselves in question.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then it will probably be like one of those ways that we described as quick and unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: But they're also seen in certain discourses as questions not to be pursued.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, am I, am I not, who am I, and so on.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, no, see, not to be pursued if you still have a view that the answer will resolve the question.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, so that is the difference between then dealing with the fact... Yeah, you are not seeking for the answer.
[SPEAKER_04]: You just want to cultivate the question...
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: ...so that it reveals the underlying pain you're trying to get rid of and endure it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, I mean, am I liable to future unwholesome states?
[SPEAKER_04]: That's a question.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's a valid question.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Many other questions that would revolve even around the Atavāda and so on, would be valid questions, if you are not
[SPEAKER_04]: As I said, seeking the answer to get rid of the discomfort of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if you're asking a question for the sake of cultivating the attitude, yeah, that's that's the whole practice of, you know, why am I doing what I'm doing, whether my intention is rooted.
[SPEAKER_04]: It all begins with a question and stays within the question.
[SPEAKER_04]: But the difference is whether you can bear it to stay on the level of the question without giving in to the temptation of, oh, but if I just get the clarification, just get the answer.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then everything is going to be fine.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then things will fall into place and then... No, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: The practice is to not overshoot it and not ignore it.
[SPEAKER_04]: I undershoot it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, yeah, that practice begins with that uncertainty of your own questionable existence.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's exactly why people would become dependent on external circumstances in terms of virtue, getting rid of doubt, even in terms of your own view of yourself.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's because you overshot the mark for so long, so many times, you develop... that's became a threshold now, of what is, as I said before.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's like when Yanavera said, it's not about finding answer to these existential questions, it's about becoming the existential questions.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, enduring them until you get used to it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, the pain of the existential questioning will go away, because it was only conditioned by your wanting to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: But the question remains.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, you realize, well, the question of this existence is the nature of existence.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's uncertain.
[SPEAKER_04]: Cannot be answered in those positive terms that you're used to operating on account of your existence.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's like, you know, existence precedes the essence.
[SPEAKER_04]: It just has to be that way.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, another slightly related but somewhat different question.
[SPEAKER_04]: We spoke about it before.
[SPEAKER_04]: I thought now we can actually...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, what's the difference then?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or rather, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: What comes first?
[SPEAKER_04]: Hindrances or fetters?
[SPEAKER_01]: Hindrance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you were saying there's this fundamental wrong view that the fetter of doubt implies.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by uprooting that, or by seeing that wrong view, one still is liable to hindrance.
[SPEAKER_04]: But not to the full extent of the fetter.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: The hindrances are, on a practical level, more fundamental.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's by not having your mind developed in regard to hindrances, all these fetters exist, that fetter you.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the reason why I bring this up is because it is quite commonly assumed other way around, whereby you think these factors are like these mystical things that will fall off when you have these deep insights of your samādhi or whatever, and hindrances are kind of come and go, and as long as you're not lustful or angry or doubtful, you're free from them.
[SPEAKER_04]: Actually, you're not.
[SPEAKER_04]: Liability, as we discovered in other talks, liability to hindrances, so liability to lust arising, means you're still within the domain of lust.
[SPEAKER_04]: You have not surmounted it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thus, if you surmount one of them properly, you surmounted all five.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because people do.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I heard even, like, teachings being sort of taught by saying, well, no, you just look, like, in terms of lust, for example, like, most of the time, you're not lustful.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thus, your practice is going well.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like, no, that's not the measure.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, a person in coma is most of the time not lustful, because he's unconscious.
[SPEAKER_04]: Does that mean he's going towards enlightenment?
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you can be most of the time not lustful or angry, but could lust arise.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you're uncertain in regard to that, means you're well within the domain of lust, domain of the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because by same logic, then, you could say, well, most of the time, you're not engaging in a sexual intercourse.
[SPEAKER_04]: And when you do, even such engagement doesn't last as long as most of the time when you're not engaging.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thus, most of the time, you're celibate.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that's not how celibacy works.
[SPEAKER_04]: Most of the time, you don't kill anybody.
[SPEAKER_04]: And if you were to kill somebody, it would last for a second only.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, most of the time, you're keeping the precepts of not killing.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_04]: Could I kill somebody?
[SPEAKER_04]: Could I engage in sensuality?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Your mind is then within the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, most of the time you shouldn't be doing it, and while you're not doing it, you should then start looking at the liability of doing it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or, could I do it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, that is a problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: There is no safety there.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if we measure whether there is a problem or not by the duration of how long you do it, well, you can get away with everything then, because, you know, most of those things wouldn't last as long as, you know, not doing those things.
[SPEAKER_04]: Say, you have never heard about a Buddhist teaching.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, for whatever reason, or through whatever teaching, you are actually practicing towards freedom from the liability to five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not just whether they're actually present or not, you are surmounting them as a whole.
[SPEAKER_04]: In other words, you're developing the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, in your case, without any instruction of the Buddhist teaching,
[SPEAKER_04]: Even the first three fetters, let's say like that, won't be as fettering.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because the mind is not fueling them anymore through wrong attitude and acting out of hindrances.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's exactly how in the suttas, some monks or people or like even followers of other practices, met the Buddha, heard one sentence and became like, boom, sotāpāna, anāgāmī, instantaneously.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's because the mind has been developed beforehand, thoroughly.
[SPEAKER_04]: They just needed somebody to put the pieces together.
[SPEAKER_04]: Pieces that they have cultivated and developed and formed.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, the Buddha, after his awakening, considered who would be the first ones to understand this dhamma, which I have discovered.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it was his two teachers who actually taught him.
[SPEAKER_04]: Neither perception, no perception.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the base of nothingness.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: So imagine, imagine if the first, just a measly first jhāna, surmounted all the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_04]: An outsider develops the mind to that extent.
[SPEAKER_04]: Imagine how much more the mind of somebody who has developed neither perception nor perception outside of the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, as the Buddha himself said, oh, it's such a great loss for them that they died before they heard my teaching, because they virtually had no dust in their eyes.
[SPEAKER_04]: They were so close.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, they would have seen this very quickly.
[SPEAKER_04]: They would have probably not even finished the sentence.
[SPEAKER_04]: They would have known exactly what he's talking about.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because the work has been done.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's why even throughout the day, if you're surmounting the hindrances, by not acting out, by enduring, by recognizing the present liability of hindrances...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, see, they are not directly present.
[SPEAKER_04]: You could say, oh, lust is absent, anger is absent, but it is present as a possibility.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you need to start to see that and endure that.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are actually practicing towards jhāna.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even if you don't sit cross-legged and watch your nostrils.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, especially if you don't sit cross-legged and watch your nostrils.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, but you see, the possibility of something means that one needs to become sensitive to the, let's say, negative aspect of experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: Something isn't happening, but could be happening.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: And how does one become sensitive to that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you become sensitive to that by practicing sensitivity of bodily sensations and concentration?
[SPEAKER_04]: Could you, let's say like that, could you become sensitive to that by doing meditation techniques and focusing practices?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that wouldn't be... that wouldn't be the main thing that makes that happen.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, basically, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, you know, any such practice as we just established is on the level of attending to objects.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means all you're going to be training yourself is attending to more specific objects within objects.
[SPEAKER_03]: And this is not on that level.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, first, you need to be able to endure it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's how you will become more sensitive to those things, to those liabilities.
[SPEAKER_04]: By not acting out, by enduring, by not trying to get rid of the discomfort of pressure to act out, but by enduring it and not acting out.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, not covering it up and not acting out.
[SPEAKER_04]: The result is, oh, you're going to become very sensitive.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're gonna see it even before you feel it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, now you're very discerning of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's that's exactly the practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: And this is also how dwelling bodily secluded, not having other people around, that give a sort of confirmation, like I exist, I'm this way, that way, and so on, to not
[SPEAKER_03]: We don't talk much, because most of the time, talking also has this sort of, let us say, interpersonal domain of wanting to be acknowledged, wanting to be understood, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: This can easily feed into this whole assumption of self, and this is what I am, and this is how I'm seen.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, when you just get out of that situation, it, well, not necessarily by itself, but it certainly moves into the direction of having this sort of background uncertainty,
[SPEAKER_03]: around your existence, become more salient, put a sensory strength on top of that, and the whole situation basically begins to sort of cook and boil a bit, without needing to make any effort positively in order to get somewhere.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: This becomes the positive effort.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which is basically negative.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, like, protecting the certain circumstances, recognizing what it would be detrimental, and then avoiding it before you do it, that's your inverted comma positive effort.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: But from the point of view of what's usually assumed to be the positive effort of practice, yeah, this is a negative effort of practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: This is stuff you don't do, so that your practice arises as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, and then the inverted situation of that would be to sit with a group of people focusing on the tip of your nose.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a very much specific thing you do.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And just generally the... even say... even if you're not engaging with other... with company, just... and if you... if you... like, you know, if you're free from atavāda and so on, so there is no perpetuation of such assumptions and validations and so on.
[SPEAKER_04]: Still, engaging with others, talking, company, is distracting on its own.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: It takes away the mind from itself.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even in neutral terms.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even if it's a neutral type of engagement.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's why solitude is necessary.
[SPEAKER_04]: Physical solitude is necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: One would think, eh... being among people could be a good exercise to, eh... be able to control, not control, but to be able to, eh... deal with these things.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean... Well, that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're not supposed to deal with them.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're supposed to uproot them.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not about learning how to deal.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, if you want to learn how to deal, being with people, you know, getting a psychotherapy degree, all of that, it's probably going to be helpful, your management.
[SPEAKER_04]: But dhamma is not a management, it's uprooting.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's the question you should ask yourself.
[SPEAKER_04]: Do I want to deal with these things?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or do I just want to uproot them once and for all?
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, more drastic measures need to be taken, such as not relying on people and not relying on learning the skill of management, because that requires to be affected first.
[SPEAKER_00]: But one could say, okay, I'm secluded, I don't talk to anybody, and now I see... it appears that, you know, I have...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not acting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it... if you are with other people, you can...
[SPEAKER_00]: They can do something, you could...
[SPEAKER_04]: Right.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, see, that's the problem there, is that you can't see whether you're liable to greed, aversion, delusion, without external help and circumstances prodding you and pushing you, which means you have not developed what needs to be developed.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, yes, circumstances can remind you of these things, but if you need circumstances to remind you, means you are not seeing the liability that doesn't need circumstances.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_04]: You are liable to be affected by things when you are not being affected by them directly.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if the only way for you to recognize that you are liable is to be affected in the first place, means, phew, more work and sensory strength will be required, because, again, that's the level you need to really transcend and get beyond.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you want to be secluded and it will enough?
[SPEAKER_04]: It should be enough for you to just ask yourself, can the lust arise?
[SPEAKER_04]: And if you're unclear, that's enough for you to know that, yes, I am liable.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then you train in regard to that question and in regard to that liability.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not, oh, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thus, let me go and seek the external lust to confirm that I could.
[SPEAKER_04]: The fact is that you don't know means, yes, that's the answer.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can be affected because you don't know whether you can or cannot be affected.
[SPEAKER_04]: And for that person,
[SPEAKER_04]: Being prompted by others... yeah, sure, somebody... Buddha can come and, out of compassion, tell you something more, and then, kind of, make you think better, and so on.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, the way... well, at least the way I understood what you said initially, was being with others is good, because it will remind you of greed, aversion, delusion, and the work you need to do.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, it will remind you of acute greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the only reason that's possible is because you're already not seeing the liability of those things.
[SPEAKER_04]: And for that, seclusion is necessary.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's quite a common view though.
[SPEAKER_03]: People saying like, okay, I'm living together with someone.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_03]: We are occasionally pushing one another's, like, pushing one another's buttons.
[SPEAKER_03]: All of this is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: I have to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: But even then, you know, having your buttons pressed, if you are half reasonable, you might develop some patience or endurance, but it is all within the domain of sensuality still.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, again, and even if you don't have anybody pressing your buttons, if you're honest with yourself, you could recognize that my buttons could be pressed, and that's enough for somebody who has developed the mind sufficiently to begin practicing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but that's almost...
[SPEAKER_04]: They could be pressed, means that's it.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is a form of pressed.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't need others external... Again, we come back to that requiring that certain assumed threshold of what is.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, an actual last aversion delusion is what last aversion delusion is.
[SPEAKER_04]: The only way to deal with liability
[SPEAKER_04]: With possibility of last aversion delusion is to actively engage with last aversion delusion.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's other way around.
[SPEAKER_04]: You need to stop engaging, so to see liability correctly.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then you will have no need to engage.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: And there is a difference there, that we can now obviously differentiate.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, are you paired with another person in a sense of a teacher?
[SPEAKER_04]: Who is not pushing your buttons in terms of lust, aversion, delusion, but giving instruction necessary for practice?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or are you just paired with random strangers that you're just clashing with emotionally and so on, due to circumstances, history or whatever else?
[SPEAKER_04]: Those are two very different... You can say, well, see, both are company, but they're very different types of company.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's exactly what, what was it, the rhinoceros says, the sutta.
[SPEAKER_04]: Don't seek company just with anyone.
[SPEAKER_04]: Only with equal or better than yourself.
[SPEAKER_04]: And even then, it's for the purpose of learning.
[SPEAKER_04]: If it's not for that purpose, that company should not be cultivated.
[SPEAKER_04]: Now, you might be stuck in certain companies, which you have to endure, but if you now start justifying that for your practice, that's... that's a cover-up.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's a cover-up.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, same or better in terms of virtue, composure and understanding.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the views, yes, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Same or better.
[SPEAKER_04]: Equal or higher.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Now, obviously, as I said,
[SPEAKER_04]: Where are you going to find that today?
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, how many people would seek that?
[SPEAKER_04]: So you need to recognize, okay, the circumstances I'm in are not the most favorable, but let me at least not cover them up.
[SPEAKER_04]: Endure the discomfort of it, and that might make rise to some other choices that I have not considered, that might be beneficial for my practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: But those choices will not arise, if you try to justify your circumstances, cover them up, and kind of ignore what you know need to be done, such as, yeah, sense of strength, guarding the sense of seclusion, not engagement, solitude, discerning these liabilities, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, non-distraction.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, do I spend... how do I spend my time throughout the day?
[SPEAKER_04]: Am I engaging for the sake of company, for the sake of distraction, for the sake of boredom?
[SPEAKER_04]: Again, household or not, it applies the same.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's the same rooted motivation.
[SPEAKER_04]: Where is it rooted in?
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, you might recognize, well, it's a bit too much to do this right away, but you mustn't cover it up.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, it's too much to do right away.
[SPEAKER_04]: I must make myself able to do it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Eventually.
[SPEAKER_04]: Later on.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not like, oh, it's too much now.
[SPEAKER_04]: I can afford to not think about it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yet, at the same time, entertain this notion that you are still practicing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, and then, there can also be the view that practice and study is about, in that sense, gaining or accumulating something, whereas, actually, it's about abandoning things.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's about undoing, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's about undoing rather than adding something, rather than keeping what is already going on, and then adding something to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Some sort of spiritual layer to your life, let's say.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whereas, actually, it's about taking things away from what you are already doing, which then will create more favorable circumstances and a sort of space to to see what's the next step, experientially.
[SPEAKER_04]: How would you take away... Maybe somebody else can join.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_04]: How would you take away those things that you know you need to take away?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like what you just said.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, first of all, by seeing the danger in perpetuating those things... What would those things be, in broad terms?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, this is obviously the whole domain of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sensuality would be one of them, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that would be the main one.
[SPEAKER_03]: And all... Because, you see, we can say sensuality, but it might not be clear what actually encompasses this whole domain of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's now another question.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's easy to keep coming back to this point, but to just see where sensuality begins and ends, so to speak, already implies... That can be a separate talk.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, because, in a sense, that whole domain needs to have ceased in order for you to have the direct knowledge what is the extent of the domain.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So...
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's not going...
[SPEAKER_04]: But if somebody who doesn't know the extent of their domain, but they want to start undoing things, as we said...
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, of course, you know, you take on the precepts.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Guard the sense doors.
[SPEAKER_04]: Where else do you look for the undoing?
[SPEAKER_04]: Where would you find internally what you need to undo?
[SPEAKER_04]: Even if you don't have any specific information or you need to undo this or this or this, there is a certain thing you can find that's uniformly present in everything that you need to undo.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, it's a basic self-forgetfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like when somebody is doing something,
[SPEAKER_03]: Whether it is going to a restaurant, being absorbed in food and pleasant circumstances, binge-watching television series and so on, what is pleasant about that is the unawareness of existence and the burden that comes with it.
[SPEAKER_04]: What is in common to eating in a restaurant, pleasure of distraction, pleasure of forgetfulness?
[SPEAKER_04]: What is the uncommon... what is a common trait?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not distraction, is it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Dearness.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_04]: Dearness, that's, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, what's, what, like, things that are dear to you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why are they dear to you?
[SPEAKER_04]: Anything that's dear, that you regard as friendly, including your own mind, as the sutta says, you should see it as an enemy, as an assassin.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why are you regarding it as dear and friendly?
[SPEAKER_04]: You don't see the danger.
[SPEAKER_04]: And when something is not dangerous, how is it felt?
[SPEAKER_04]: Pleasant.
[SPEAKER_04]: Safe.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's that safety.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which, of course, it's felt pleasant.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, any safety you find in anything, you can start undermining that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that would be different things.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why there is no external set.
[SPEAKER_04]: Some people will find safety in doing certain things, in certain habits, in access to certain things.
[SPEAKER_04]: Some people will find something else.
[SPEAKER_04]: What is in common is, you do find a sense of safety in it.
[SPEAKER_04]: In something.
[SPEAKER_04]: In doing something, in having something, in belonging to something.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if you follow the thread of where you find safety and keep pulling it out, yeah, you are going in the right direction.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because then there will be nothing that you find safe in this world and that's the true disenchantment and dispassion that will result in arahantship.
[SPEAKER_04]: But see, in order to do that, you need to be able to endure such lack of safety without losing your mind or breaking down or distracting yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but we're talking about safety here in the context of one's existence.
[SPEAKER_03]: We're not talking about whether you put on your safety belt in the car or not.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, no, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I'm not saying, like, don't put on your seat belt in the car.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, right, right.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: See, undoing the sense of... the thread of what... where you find safety in, does not mean exposing yourself to danger.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's my point.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no, quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you don't need to go external, extreme circumstances.
[SPEAKER_04]: You just recognize there are things, see, because you are not an arahant, means you are resting upon something, upon some possessions, some value, some ideas.
[SPEAKER_04]: Either way, you are finding safety in them.
[SPEAKER_04]: To that extent, you feel sheltered.
[SPEAKER_04]: Start questioning that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Start putting that in question, undermining it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And there it is, the most acute practice you can have, if you can hold it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's actually one of the four summaries of the dhamma, that, you know, this world is without shelter and protection.
[SPEAKER_03]: It literally says that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Through and through.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, there's nothing.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it's similar in other sutras.
[SPEAKER_04]: He realized there is nothing worth holding on, possessing, clinging to, whatever you want to translate it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, to that extent, you'll be undermined by it.
[SPEAKER_04]: That was what you were telling the other day, that renunciation is getting out of the security... Like, even if you don't necessarily see all these, like, nuances, if you start keeping the precepts, like, rightly, not just on a level of external authority, but because you choose to do so, and you keep choosing to do so every single time, yeah, that renunciation is emulating that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Basically, that undermining of things that you're taking for granted, that giving up, that relinquishment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And renunciating the household life is even more, I mean, getting out of your security.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, see, sometimes people can renounce immediate things that provide you with safety, but they cannot renounce
[SPEAKER_04]: The need for maybe access to safety.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, I'm not accessing it now, but I would like to have an option to access it if I need to.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, to that extent, you are still not truly putting yourself in that position of uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's like, okay, yeah, I'm not engaging with this, but if push comes to shove, I could, and that in itself will offer you safety.
[SPEAKER_04]: The possibility that you could engage with things that you used to engage with for the sake of safety and relief and pleasure and so on, that's enough.
[SPEAKER_04]: That becomes then your safety, your relief, your pleasure.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm not doing it, but I would if I'm pressed far enough.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's something you actually need to abandon.
[SPEAKER_04]: You need to give up and just... just decide, no, I won't, even if my life depends on it, I won't engage with it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then it feels very differently.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's kind of similar to what we spoke before, like, in terms of sensuality and giving up the addiction.
[SPEAKER_04]: Try to give up cigarettes or similar, and then it's like, oh, yes, I'm not...
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm not smoking currently.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if the need comes up, I could.
[SPEAKER_04]: And they're fine with that idea.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it's like, no, you shouldn't be fine with that idea.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you should even decide on the level of, if a need comes up, no, never again.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then it feels very different.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then the weight is much more serious.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the Buddha gave the similar sutra, the simile of the quail.
[SPEAKER_04]: He says, sometimes I make a little rule and say, monks, don't do that.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it's a little.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's insignificant.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then some monks say, well, that's insignificant.
[SPEAKER_04]: So they do it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then some other monks say, well, that's insignificant.
[SPEAKER_04]: So they make the effort and abandon it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it's insignificant.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why would you then do it?
[SPEAKER_04]: And the Buddha said, the monks that...
[SPEAKER_04]: It's truly insignificant.
[SPEAKER_04]: But the ones that don't abandon it, they're like a quail that's tied down with insignificant rotten, half-rotten ropes.
[SPEAKER_04]: But because it's a weak quail, those such ropes are enough to keep it bound.
[SPEAKER_04]: The ones that abandon even the seemingly insignificant things are basically like elephants tied with leather straps.
[SPEAKER_04]: But they would, because they're elephants, they would break the leather straps.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, in other words, things feel insignificant because you're not abandoning them.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you master the determination to say no in the ultimate sense, you realize they're leather straps, actually.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it's easy to go, oh, no, no, this is just a rope.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just a rotten rope.
[SPEAKER_04]: This is not a bond.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because you're not committing to abandoning it.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's when it will be felt differently.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you decide in that ultimate sense, never again.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then you feel the weight.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then you, oh, it's an actual strap.
[SPEAKER_04]: A leather strap.
[SPEAKER_04]: But because you have decided such thing and abstained from such actions, you become an elephant that can break even the leather straps.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, so by abandoning that possibility of coming back to it in the future, all the weight is, let us say, concentrated in the present, which is where the burden is fully felt.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, the burden of the entire extent.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: All the future possible, it doesn't matter now, it's the same determination covering it all, never again.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, but when that possibility is there, like, I might come back to it in the future, this is... That's it, that's a relief.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that precisely, so the burden in the present is not felt, because there is this sort of time interval, like, in the future somewhere, this could still exist for me, and consequently the problem is not seen now.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you say you give up sensuality, or never
[SPEAKER_02]: I won't use sensuality as a distraction or escape from the pain I feel, the agitation I feel.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I won't ever go in that direction again.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ever.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you feel, now what do I...?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, I don't know what to do.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't know what to do now, but I know what I will not do.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you feel...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, then you have to endure it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Endure that lack of safety, but not compromise the direction you know you shouldn't go.
[SPEAKER_04]: And once you endure it long enough, you get to see where to go and what to do.
[SPEAKER_04]: And if there is anything you need to do.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, this is this negative approach again.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not about finding something positively to move towards.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's about abandoning that future possibility.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And not sustaining that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: That future possibility.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you get to see the dhamma if you basically remove all of your attitudes, views, preconceived notions that are covering it up.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even the Buddha himself.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the only way we can do it.
[SPEAKER_04]: He said, oh, it's like finding the ancient path that was covered and I uncovered it.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you don't get to see the dhamma by doing practices on top of everything else, all the views and notions and preconceived ideas.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, that's just piling up, piling up, piling up, piling up of wrong views.
[SPEAKER_04]: If those things are not seen as a result of undoing all of your views, notions, habits and so on, it's going to be on the level of wrong practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because any view that one holds is rooted in this sense of safety, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, the right view begins by recognizing that the right practice is about undoing all of your safety stances, internally.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's still technically a view, but it's a view that actually undermines need for views.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's when arahant, eventually, when he becomes an arahant, is gone beyond the views.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, even the right view is gone in him, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_04]: Ceased.
[SPEAKER_04]: No need for it anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because the views have been extinguished.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's what the views are.
[SPEAKER_04]: Standpoints of safety.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, we've touched on it last time.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_02]: When?
[SPEAKER_02]: We did.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, we wanted to speak about it again, the safety, the pleasure that comes from views, of why you hold on to your views.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: You abandon sensuality, sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you start holding on to views.
[SPEAKER_04]: The safety of the views, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, yeah, very much so.
[SPEAKER_04]: The conviction, the certainty.
[SPEAKER_02]: It protects you from pain.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why people double down in these views once they... And the suttas say that once samanas and brāhmaṇas withdraw from sensuality, then they start adhering, i.e.
[SPEAKER_04]: doubling down even harder to the views.
[SPEAKER_04]: And again, views not on the level of these metaphysical ideas of cosmos.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: Views on the level of you shouldn't be sitting like that, and he shouldn't be speaking like that, or how can he do this, how can they do that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Those are the views.
[SPEAKER_04]: All of those are the views, and that's exactly what Samanins and Brahmins fall out over.
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, they live keeping the same rules, same environment, and then they absolutely kind of... their minds lose perspective on account of just these stance... standpoints.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because I find it comforting and I find sense of safety if things are done this way.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's my view.
[SPEAKER_04]: And if I take that view for granted, now I will require other people to do things that way, because I am being compromised by others not following these external set of circumstances that I established upon... my safety upon.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, would you say that that is fetter of Śrīla Bhāgavatam Pāramāsa?
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's exactly what Śrīla Bhāgavatam Pāramāsa is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why, like, it's not enough for you to just be virtuous to approve the fetter of Śrīla Bhāgavatam Pāramāsa.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: The view of management, as we said before
[SPEAKER_03]: What do you mean?
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, go to another safe place for another hunt.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, it's exactly that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Abandoning any need for safety.
[SPEAKER_04]: Having nothing to protect.
[SPEAKER_04]: Relinquishing anything that would require protection.
[SPEAKER_04]: Means then you're safe, because nothing can be threatened.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: As reflecting on sickness, that is the example.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Fundamental.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sickness, aging, death.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the fundamental underminer.
[SPEAKER_03]: Seeing sickness as a possibility is going to cut through all the safety and comfort of having a house, having something to eat, sensual pleasures, clothing.
[SPEAKER_03]: All of that suddenly loses perspective if
[SPEAKER_03]: This body can basically break apart and you have to experience on your own... That's a good example.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, how would you then sustain such... Like, say, a householder or a monk, you might get a spur of, you know, contemplating sickness that cuts through your sense of safety, but then it fades away.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then you lose that edge.
[SPEAKER_04]: How would you sustain that edge?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, this is going towards the direction of right recollection.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is it that you're actually bringing to mind?
[SPEAKER_04]: And the more the mind... Well, it's the same things you recollected before.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're doing the same recollections, but there is no more edge to it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, either because the work has all been done, or, well, there can be a tendency that just thinking about something is the same as enduring the actual uncertainty, which it is not.
[SPEAKER_04]: The present of a thought need not be experienced.
[SPEAKER_04]: But why would that happen?
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, something you've endured, now it just went into you, just thinking about it, and it's not felt anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because what started out as an authentic practice, gradually becomes a way of finding safety.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sure, but why?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's removed from the situation, my present situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, or, because the mind...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, why would you lose a sense of urgency?
[SPEAKER_04]: Say, you're thinking the same things... Because it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_04]: There was a sense of urgency.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then it fades away, even when you really try to to get it back.
[SPEAKER_03]: But a craving comes in to use all of that to award... to ward off unpleasant feelings.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it transforms into a management technique again, which is missing the point.
[SPEAKER_04]: Could be.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're putting it in front of you, like... Could be.
[SPEAKER_04]: But why would you be doing all of that?
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the real...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's like... Say, as I said, you start contemplating sickness that comes through... cuts through the sense of safety.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you feel that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you're very alert as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: But then it fades away.
[SPEAKER_04]: Did you do something wrong?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or it just happens on its own?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or... How can you then get that sense of urgency back?
[SPEAKER_04]: That the edge is gone.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why does the edge go away?
[SPEAKER_04]: Why can't you just sustain that edge up until you're an arahant?
[SPEAKER_04]: Why did the Buddha have to remind even, eh... sekhas, the noble disciples, that they still have work to do?
[SPEAKER_03]: Why would then they... why do people... why does the mind become complacent?
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's really the question here.
[SPEAKER_03]: Any ideas?
[SPEAKER_03]: Why does the mind become complacent?
[SPEAKER_04]: Even, like, you know, you're clear, so it's not on the level of, oh, I think I know what sickness is.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, you actually know what sickness is.
[SPEAKER_04]: It cuts through possessions and safety, but then you still become complacent.
[SPEAKER_04]: Does that complacency... Do you ever say in it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Do you do anything that results in it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or it just happens?
[SPEAKER_00]: You come back to your safety, that you are not in that moment.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, you can come back to it in your mind, but you don't feel that edge anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, why is that?
[SPEAKER_04]: Why is it covered up?
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not seeing it.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's obvious.
[SPEAKER_04]: You won't be seeing it because it's covered up.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, why are you not seeing it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Why is it covered up?
[SPEAKER_04]: We actually answered it before that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, no, when we said about... Well, yes, sure.
[SPEAKER_04]: But no, when we said about the whole practice, it's about uncovering things.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if things get covered up, such as this edge gets covered up, means your circumstances, your choices that you make, need to be upgraded, need to change.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you cannot directly access that edge anymore, because it was covered up.
[SPEAKER_04]: By what?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, by lack of seclusion, by company,
[SPEAKER_04]: By distraction, by still choosing greed, aversion, delusion on some level of action.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you start...
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, if you start thinking like this, you can get... then you... if the edge disappears, you use that as a symptom.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you don't just try to... oh, let me just contemplate and revoke that novelty of that edge of sickness.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: I can't do that.
[SPEAKER_04]: It will be covered up.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why?
[SPEAKER_04]: So, am I liable to covering up the sense of urgency?
[SPEAKER_04]: There can be another line of reasoning you can use, similar to other lines of reasoning in the suttas that I would encourage.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, and that's my point.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it doesn't get covered up on its own.
[SPEAKER_04]: It will disappear, the edge, either because you're an arahant, exactly as you said,
[SPEAKER_04]: All because your choices and actions and circumstances that you've been tolerating on certain levels are resulting in accumulation that covers it up.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, even that contemplation of sickness needs to be seen in a wider context, and if this edge goes off, then, rather than...
[SPEAKER_04]: There are only two reasons, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Either arahantship or a cover-up.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Surely, it won't be on the level of a putujanas cover-up, when he just ignores and so on.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, if the edge is gone, if that uncertainty, the back onto the very start of this long talk, when you were existing as a question,
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, the pain of that can disappear if you practice rightly, but the question remains, because the anicca remains.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it's that anicca that then prevents you to commit, to find safety in things that are uncertain, find ownership in things that are uncertain.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the discomfort of that question, the sense of urgency of that question, will disappear if you're either an arahant or if you cover it up.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's exactly what the Buddha needed to encourage even sekkers who would become complacent.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you can keep asking, what haven't I abandoned?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, is it... no, just ask yourself, do I feel the sense of urgency?
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, is it because I'm an arahant?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, if the answer to that is no, then it's because I'm covering it up.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you should start feeling urgency in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And how do I cover it up?
[SPEAKER_04]: Is it just an accident?
[SPEAKER_04]: Accidental cover-up?
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: How am I spending my day?
[SPEAKER_04]: What are the choices I'm making throughout the day?
[SPEAKER_04]: What are my states of mind?
[SPEAKER_04]: That's how I'm covering it up.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's always intentional choices.
[SPEAKER_04]: These mistakes, obstructions, cannot happen accidentally.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's my whole point.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, practically speaking, it's going to come down to, okay, so, am I secluded enough?
[SPEAKER_04]: Is most of my daily time spent in company, in work, in talking, in thinking things that are secondary?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or do I actually try and protect that, so that, indirectly, I protect the context of the sense of urgency being covered up?
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, those are all the obstacles for the seka.
[SPEAKER_03]: The lighting in work.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sleeping a lot.
[SPEAKER_03]: Talking, sleeping.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, talking.
[SPEAKER_04]: But even for a non-seeker, who wants to, as I said, start to endure things rightly, you need that sense of urgency.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, you know, you can think about it when there is no distraction, when you're alone, but then you engage with duties, with speaking, with doing this, with doing that, and you kind of forget, or you don't feel the question mark anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: You know it's there, theoretically, abstractly, you'll give the same answer, but you don't feel it the same way.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's seclusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not putting yourself in a dangerous position.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's why seclusion is necessary.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is precisely what the Buddha says, or asked Ananda to instruct like those who have newly gone forth.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's these five things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Keep the patimokkha.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, secondly, sense restraint, don't talk much, dwell bodily secluded, and work on the right view.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Those are the five things for anyone who has left the household life and goes forth.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, just to do that, regardless of any methods or techniques to put yourself in that situation, and then not come to morning and evening meetings, but just go and pīṇapārtha and have the patimokkha every fortnight, and other than that, you are on your own.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's gonna... well, it seems to me... well, this is going to expose everything that we just talked about.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, then, the question comes down to how do you prevent... sorry, the answer comes down to the question of how do you prevent losing the edge of the sense of urgency.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like, start sort of, you know, reflecting upon and broadening your questioning in context, so to find all the indirect things that you are still doing,
[SPEAKER_04]: So, yeah, I keep the precepts and all this, but I don't feel it anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, are you sufficiently secluded?
[SPEAKER_04]: Are you sufficiently withdrawn?
[SPEAKER_04]: How about your mental states?
[SPEAKER_04]: Do they still revolve around greed?
[SPEAKER_04]: All these little things that are not as bad, obviously, as before, now are bad enough to cover up.
[SPEAKER_04]: So now you have to remove the finer ones, but now they are the impurities.
[SPEAKER_04]: Now they're the only impurities, thus they are the ones that are covering it up now.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that can only be done once the core stuff is sort of out of the way.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, restraint by body, by speech, by patimokha, by precepts, sensory strain, guarding of the sense doors, sure.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, that was just the beginning.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if the sense of urgency, if the edge, if the question mark is not felt anymore, means now there is a time for a next layer of removal of the cover-up.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.